Guide to the Julia Ellsworth Ford Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Julia Ellsworth Ford papers
1874-1951
YCAL MSS 638
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.17
(16 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, scrapbooks, printed material, photographs, and other papers, documenting aspects of the life and work of Julia Ellsworth Ford and her relationships with literary and artistic figures of the early 20th century, including, among others, John Butler Yeats and William Butler Yeats.
Ford, Julia Ellsworth, 1859-1950
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Julia Ellsworth Ford, 1951.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Julia Ellsworth Ford (1859-1950)
Julia Ellsworth Ford was a New York socialite, art collector and patron, and author of children's books. She was married to Simeon Ford, a financier and co-owner of the Grand Union Hotel in New York. Ford presided over a salon that included the Lebanese mystic Kahlil Gibran, Irish poet W. B. Yeats, and American dancer Isadora Duncan. Her published works include: Simeon Solomon: An Appreciation (1908), Imagina (1914), and Snickerty Nick (1919), among others.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, scrapbooks, printed material, photographs, and other papers, documenting aspects of the life and work of Julia Ellsworth Ford and her relationships with literary and artistic figures of the early 20th century, including, among others, John Butler Yeats and W. B. Yeats.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1902-1949. II. Writings, circa 1874-1951. III. Scrapbooks, 1903-1951. IV. Other Papers, 1881-1950.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Ford, Julia Ellsworth, 1859-1950; Yeats, John Butler, 1839-1922; Yeats, W. B. (William Butler), 1865-1939
- Correspondence, 1902-1949; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Addams, Jane, 1927 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alma-Tadema, Lawrence, Sir, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Augell, Norman, 1917-1919, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bangs, John Kendrick, 1902-1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Barnard, George Grey, 1911-1916 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Barrie, J. M., 1915 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Beaux, Cecilia, 1914 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Binyon, Lawrence, 1913 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bragdon, Claude Fayette, [19--] January 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Buck, Pearl S., 1944 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Byner, Witter, 1913-1919 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Carman, Bliss, 1916 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Canaan, Gilbert, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chaplin, Charlie, 1936 February 16 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chiang, May-ling Soong, 1940 February 6-April 19 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Churchill, Winston, [19--] December 3 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Coburn, Mr. and Mrs., undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Colum, Padraic, 1914 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Colvin, Sidney, 1903 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Craig, Edward Gordon, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Dargan, Olive, 1915-1948 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - De la Mare, Walter, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - De Lanux, Pierre, 1919 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Deutsch, Babette, 1941 April 21 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Earhart, Amelia, 1931 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Ford, Lauren, 1941-1950 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Frost, Robert, 1916 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Galsworthy, John, 1919 April 18, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Gibran, Kahlil, 1914 April 8 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Graham, Stephen, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Granville-Barker, Harley, 1915 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gregory, Lady, 1911 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Hacker, Arthur, 1902, circa 1916 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Hampden, Walter, 1933 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Hill, Anne, 1911-1914 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Holmes, John Haynes, 1945 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Hossain, Syud, 1924 October (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Housman, Laurence, 1916-1930 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Huneker, James, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Hurst, Fannie, 1945 March 2 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Kingston, Gertrude, 1914-1916 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Kreymborg, Alfred, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Lamont, Thomas W., 1907-1938 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - La Motte, Ellen Newbold, 1924 April 22 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Leslie, Shane, 1912 March 22 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Littell, Philip, 1918 February 6 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Locke, William John, 1909-1910 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Long, Haniel, 1918-1931 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Lowell, Amy, 1916-1920 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - MacKaye, Percy, 1909-1949 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - MacMonnies, Frederick William, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Markey, Alexander, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Markham, Edwin, 1919 April 20 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Masefield, John, 1916-1926 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Masters, Edgar Lee, 1915 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Matthison, Edith Wynne, 1909-1942 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Meynell, Alice, 1914, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Meynell, Francis, 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Morel, E. D., 1923-1925 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Mosher, Thomas Bird, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - O'Neill, Rose Cecil, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Page, Walter Hines, 1913 November (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Peabody, Josephine Preston, 1911-1916 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Pound, Ezra, 1911 February 24 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Pyle, Howard, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Rackham, Arthur, 1912-1916 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Reed, John, no year April 14 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Robinson, Edwin Arlington, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Rolland, Romain, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Rossetti, William Michael, 1903, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Rothenstein, William, undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Russell, Bertrand, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Sassoon, Siegfried, 1920 February 16 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Sharp, Elizabeth A., 1911 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - St. Denis, Ruth, 1910, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Stuck, Franz, Ritter von, 1902, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Teasdale, Sara, 1912, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Terry, Ellen, Dame, 1915-1921 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Waterhouse, John William, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Wells, H. G., 1916 November 2 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Willcox, Louise Collier, 1907 July 15 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Wong, Anna May, 1933 April 1 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Wylie, Elinor, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Yale University Library, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Yeats, Elizabeth Corbet, 1906-1939 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Yeats, Georgie, 1920 January 29, undated (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Yeats, Jack Butler, 1904 April 22 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Yeats, John Butler, 1911-1921 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Yeats, W. B., 1908 (Box 3, Folder 89)
- Writings, circa 1874-1951; Series II; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Writings of Julia Ellsworth Ford, arranged alphabetically by title, and Writings about Julia Ellsworth Ford by Francis H. Bangs.
  - Writings of Julia Ellsworth Ford
    - Akhnaton: Pharaoe and Prophet
      - Published version, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 90)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 91)
      - Revised typescript, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - "A Delightful Discovery," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - "E. D. Morel, M. P.," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - "The Gift of the Spirit," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 95)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes hand printed manuscript, illustrated with vine and flower border motif by Charles Braithwaite.
    - "Inner Vision," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - "Julia's Novel," autograph manuscript, circa 1874 (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - "Julia's Novel," typescript, circa 1874 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - "A National Menace," typescript, 1918-1945 (Box 4, Folder 99)
      Includes Ford's correspondence, clippings, and booklets about hayfever and ragweed.
    - Snickerty Nick
      - Publication Material, 1914-1919 (Box 4, Folder 100)
        Includes book announcements and portfolio of color plate illustrations for Imagina, illustrated by Ford's daughter, Lauren Ford, and Snickerty Nick, illustrated by Arthur Rackham.
      - Plays, typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 101)
        Includes: Snickerty Nick and the merry-go-round horses, a play in 5 scenes by Julia Ellsworth Ford and Muriel Smith. Snickerty Nick conquers the dragon, a play in 3 scenes by Julie Ellsworth Ford and Jean Muir. Snickerty Nick and Buzzy the pirate bee, a play in 5 scenes by Julia Ellsworth Ford. Snickerty Nick and the 3 bears, a play in 5 scenes by Julia Ellsworth Ford.
    - "Temple of the Universal Spirit," typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - "Walt Whitman, Seer and Poet," typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Walt Whitman, typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 104)
      Untitled work about the relationship between Walt Whitman and Anne Burrows Gilchrist. Also includes correspondence from Ford to Grace Gilchrist, Anne Burrows Gilchrist's daughter with 2 photographs of Walt Whitman.
    - "Discarded notes", 1896-1951 (Box 5, Folder 105)
      Includes autobiographical material, "Looking Forward: the Memoirs of Julia Ellsworth Ford," and essays about Ellen Terry and Isadora Duncan.
    - Unpublished writings, typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 106-107)
      Includes: Birth of the white rose. Blind in the sunlight, a play in 4 acts. Mystery on the mountain. And some have pets thrust upon them. The three little bears, Goldenlocks, Admiral T-Wee and the monkees. Also includes the cover title, Precious.
    - Unpublished writings, typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 108)
      Includes: Magic Innerland. Narneen and her playthings. Little Loneleaf, belle of the maple tree. Princess Butterfly and Buzzy the pirate bee. King Nautilus Nole.
  - Writings about Julia Ellsworth Ford by Francis H. Bangs
    - "Julia Ellsworth Ford, an appreciation, by Francis H. Bangs," typescript, circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - "Julie Ellsworth Ford, personality and patron of the arts, an appreciation, by Francis H. Bangs," typescript, circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 110)
- Scrapbooks, 1903-1951; Series III; 0.63; (7 boxes)
  - "Yeats", 1903-1943 (Box 6)
    Includes clippings, photographs, reviews, printed material and notes related to William Butler Yeats.
  - The Mist, 1913 (Box 7)
    Includes pamphlets, clippings, correspondence and miscellaneous material relating to "The mist; a little play in three scenes."
  - "Matter concerning Imagina", 1913-1924 (Box 8)
    Includes press notices, clippings, drawings, and correspondence from P. Mackaye and Olive Dargan related to Ford's book, Imagina.
  - "Something to think about", 1942-1944 (Box 9)
    Includes: Correspondence regarding the role of the Japanese and of Japanese Americans in World War II, including a copy of Ford's letter to the President of the United States; correspondence from members of the United States Senate and Congress, state and local officials and religious, political and news organizations; a copy of Ford's pamphlets with "Supplement to Something to think about," and related clippings.
  - "Concerning The Julia Ellsworth Ford Foundation for the encouragement of Juvenile literature in America", 1934-1944 (Box 10)
    Includes correspondence, clippings, a booklet and miscellaneous material.
  - "Julia Ellsworth Ford, a scrap-book of Disjecta Membra hinting at some of her doings, compiled by Francis Hyde Bangs", 1911-1951 (Box 11)
    Includes: Correspondence, clippings, promotional material, brochures, pamphlets and photographs relating to Julia Ellsworth Ford, Ruth St. Denis, Walt Whitman, and Yeats. Also includes a copy of "Isadora Duncan, the dance of the future," signed by Isadora Duncan, a descriptive bibliography of books and pamphlets by Ford, and a summary of Ford's letters given to Yale University Library.
  - "Julia Ellsworth Ford, Scrap-book no. 2. Arranged by Francis Hyde Bangs", 1906-1951 (Box 12)
    Includes: Pamphlets by Ford, book jackets illustrated by Arthur Rackham, offprints of Simeon Solomon's illustrations, an original drawing by John Butler Yeats, photographs of Ford, Walt Whitman and William Butler Yeats and signed photographs of British actress, Ellen Terry and Ruth St. Denis.
- Other Papers, 1881-1950; Series IV; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  - "Birthday Book," printed birthday record book completed in manuscript, 1881-1944 (Box 13, Folder 111)
    An illustrated "Emerson birthday book," including the names and birthdays of Ford's family, friends, acquaintances and other events.
  - Consequences, clippings, ephemera and advertisements related to Ford's book, 1929-1930 (Box 13, Folder 112)
  - Ford, Ellsworth and Lauren, clippings and materials related to their artwork, 1944-1949 (Box 13, Folder 113)
  - Ford, Julia Ellsworth, clippings, 1915-1950 (Box 13, Folder 114)
    Includes Ford's obituary
  - "Last Will and Testament of Julia Ellsworth Ford", 1947-1950 (Box 13, Folder 115)
    Includes copies of Ford's will, legal correspondence, a letter from Ford's son Hobart, named as executor of Ford's estate.
  - Poems and greeting cards by Julia Ellsworth Ford, 1949, undated (Box 14, Folder 116)
    Includes poems by Julia Ellsworth Ford, "The Bird," "The Peacock," "The Two Voices," "Things," "The Tree," "What is Eternal?," and photographs of Julia Ellsworth Ford's paintings. Also includes a poem by Olive Dragan.
  - Simeon Solomon
    - Clippings about Simeon Solomon, undated (Box 14, Folder 117)
    - Photographic reproductions of Simeon Solomon's artwork, 1887-1896 (Box 14, Folder 118-120)
  - "Snickerty Nick," motion picture production photographs, undated (Box 14, Folder 121)
  - "Snickerty Nick," clippings and promotional material, 1923-1937 (Box 14, Folder 122)
    Includes announcements for the musical production of Snickerty Nick, and advertisements for the music score by Charles Arthur Ridgway used in the Hollywood production of the movie.
  - Walt Whitman, printed material and photographs, 1894, undated (Box 15, Folder 123)
  - "Women Painters of the West," correspondence and related material, 1947, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 124)
    Includes Ford's speech and poem presented to the Women Painters of the West. Also includes related correspondence with Orpha Klinker, associated with Women Painters of the West.
  - Photographs of John Butler Yeats, William Butler Yeats and a sketch of George Russell (A. E.) by John Butler Yeats, undated (Box 15, Folder 125)
  - Printing block based on a sketch of George Russell (A. E.) by John Butler Yeats, circa 1905 (Box 15, Folder 126)
  - Printing block based on a sketch of George Russell (A. E.) by John Butler Yeats, circa 1905 (Box 15, Folder 127)
  - Printed versions of writings by Julia Ellsworth Ford
    - "The coming international opium conference," pamphlet, 1924 July (Box 16, Folder 128)
    - "Consequences," advertisements related to Ford's book, undated (Box 16, Folder 129)
    - "Opium and the British policy," pamphlet, 1925 March 2 (Box 16, Folder 130)
    - "Pan and the spirit of beauty," pamphlet, 1933 (Box 16, Folder 131)
    - "Peace depends on Great Britain," pamphlet, 1921 (Box 16, Folder 132)
    - "Something to think about," pamphlet, 1942 June 7 (Box 16, Folder 133)
    - "Spirit of Shu-Yuan Chang inspires China," pamphlet, 1938 (Box 16, Folder 134)
    - "Supplement to Something to think about," pamphlet, 1942 October 8 (Box 16, Folder 135)
    - "Tai-Shan, the holy mountain in Shan-tung," pamphlet, 1919 September 11 (Box 16, Folder 136)
    - "The temple of the universal spirit," pamphlet, 1945, March 5 (Box 16, Folder 137)
  - Photographs of Julia Ellsworth Ford, undated (Box 16, Folder 138)
  - Photographs of children, dancers, and friends of Julia Ellsworth Ford, including Kahlil Gibran, undated (Box 16, Folder 139)
  - Photographic reproductions of artwork, undated (Box 16, Folder 140)